Here's another question. Um
I've been trying to find satisfaction
through connection and a sense of
belonging within the Sangha community.
However, I'm realizing that because any
human group is inherently subject to
shifting dynamics, comings and goings,
and impermanence,
resting my internal sense of safety on
others leaves me feeling quite
vulnerable. If the fundamental nature of all social
If the fundamental nature of all social
groups is change, how can I truly take
the Sangha as a refuge? And
And
the there's a
So, that I thought I'd add this Sutta
verse. This short verse.
Um
It says, "Dwell with yourselves as an
island, with yourselves as a refuge, and
with no other refuge.
Dwell with the Dhamma as an island, with
the Dhamma as a refuge,
with no other refuge.
But there is the
you know, I take refuge in the Sangha.
>> Yeah, but I think that has been sort of
uh
unintentionally bastardized over
centuries. Um
Um
So, I think the answer to his question
is quite simple. To that question is
quite simple. You just need to upgrade
your definition of Sangha.
It's not a bunch of people that come
together for the same purpose or cause
and feel part of a community or a group.
It's literally Sangha is people that
understood the Buddhist teachings or
sotapannas or higher.
That's what Sangha is. So, when people
take refuge in Sangha, they take their
refuge in the values that those people
developed. As in like I take refuge
in those that did the work that the
Buddha outlined as something so that I
can strive towards that and become part
of that. As in do the work myself.
That's why it's like Uh
Uh
and that's what the I think it was about
when all those Arahats came together or
or maybe it wasn't that Sutta, but it
was when the Buddha was saying that the
greatest assembly is the assembly of
Arahats. And you realize it's because it's not an
And you realize it's because it's not an
assembly.
It's a collection of fully purified
individuals. Fully an island to themselves. They
Fully an island to themselves. They
don't need even the Buddha out there.
They can't even need the Buddha anymore.
It's just gone.
Fully enclosed within their
understanding, purified on account of
it. When those individuals come
together, that's the greatest Sangha,
the greatest assembly. That's kind of
the irony of it cuz they're not there as
a group. They're not there together.
They do not partake in each other's
comforts or each other's company and so
on. All of that's been cleansed away
from their being, basically.
So, taking the refuge in Sangha means
taking the refuge in
possibility of succeeding in the
training like others before you.
But doesn't mean just joining a local
Buddhist group and feeling good in the
company of others like-minded people or
something. Well, for that you don't need
the Buddhist teaching, just
>> Any group.
>> get into arts and crafts and
join the proper groups and you'll feel
the same.
>> But it's the same thing. Take refuge in
the Sangha means take refuge in the
Dhamma. >> Yeah, of course. Yeah.
>> Yeah, of course. Yeah.
Yeah, take refuge in the Buddha means
take refuge in the Dhamma, take refuge
in the Sangha, i.e. those who have
actually developed the Dhamma.
Cuz that's what Sangha is.
>> But yeah, that's
>> But yes, you have the
you know, conventional now, you know,
basically monks culturally ordained.
Um and there's no like Dhamma to begin
with, basically. You just do your
service duties, be part of the whole
setup. So, then
So, then
people who are like formally admitted to
the order are called Sangha.
>> Mhm.
>> But again, you can have the Sangha of
thousands of monks if not single one of
them is even a sotapanna, that's not a
Sangha. It's just a bunch of
householders that wear robes.
>> And I just like the idea that a
being part of a community
with the same interest and so on is
going to somehow
uh satisfy you or make
make you better is you know free from
suffering if it's a Buddhist group.
>> I suppose it can make you better
if if you yourself were unrestrained
before, had no sense of moderation or the
had no sense of moderation or the
precepts and then you join the group
that installs those values. So, it's not
like there is no conventional benefit,
but that's not really what the question
was referring to. It was referring to
that kind of uh emotional safety you
find in the comfort of like-minded
people. And that's like you might not help you
And that's like you might not help you
might not be able to help, but feel like
that. But, you certainly need to
recognize it as a trap and as an
obstacle to the actual understanding of
the Dhamma because
like how can you expect to be
independent, imperturbable, immovable by
by by the worldly winds and the big
pressures and emotional discomforts and
the the the the the the extent of the chitta
the the the the the extent of the chitta
it can take against you if you still
can't even contain uh and overcome
your quite superficial dependence on the
presence of other people because they
make me feel safe.
Because these ideas are the same and we
partake we share the common goal and if
it feels uplifted. It's like it might
feel uplifted, but you shouldn't just
take it for at face value and follow it
blindly as as as some sort of positive
thing because as I said, it it it's
actually more often than not an obstacle
to to the practice, which means it's
it's unbeneficial for you.
Because again, you're you're using it to
avoid the weight of the practice is felt
by you alone.
And that's kind of a necessary
precondition really for successful
practice is recognizing that you are
alone. That nobody can do this for you and
That nobody can do this for you and
nobody can prevent you from doing it.
Nobody can come in between you and the
Dharma practice if done successfully.
That's why it can't be taken away.
That's why it's unsurpassed, unshakable,
irreversible freedom. It doesn't depend
on anything external it including chief
of among which is the other people
really. >> Like you're the one carrying the burden.
>> Like you're the one carrying the burden.
You're the one that has to put it down.
No one else can put it down for you.
>> So it's not necessarily like I must now
say no to all the groups and never talk
to people.
Some people might kind of go the other
way too much. It's like no, you need to
learn you recognize the objective need
to
collect the right information, right
values uh
uh
uh learn about the right direction of
practice and for that you well directly
or indirectly you need an instruction of
another. Either through reading the suttas,
Either through reading the suttas,
watching the talks or if you have access
to those people
uh talking to them directly and learning
from it but not so that you can feel
safe in their company
but so that you can then when you are
alone and when eventually you are alone
uh or even before that so you can start
taking it on upon yourself to practice
rightly regardless of whether they are
others supporting or not, whether there
is a group or not, whether you feel
alone or lonely it doesn't matter. The
practice remains the same and unchanged.